Finding Aid for Stanley Schachter Papers 1945-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stanley Schachter Papers 1945-1998
Schachter, Stanley, 1922-
Social psychologist, Columbia University professor of psychology, affiliated with the Research Center for Group Dynamics; collection includes publications and professional papers.
9958 Aa 2
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were received from Sophia Schachter on December 11, 1998 (Donor no. 8794 )
The collection is open for research.
Described by his colleagues as a "brilliant experimentalist" in the field of social psychology, Dr. Stanley Schachter was not only known for his many important and influential contributions to social psychology, but to the entire field of psychology. Throughout his career, he maintained wide-ranging professional interests in areas such as: smoking and obesity, decision-making in the stock market, affiliation theory, and the effects of deviating from group decisions. The New York Times lauded him as "Psychologist of the Mundane." Indeed, Schachter had a knack for conducting imaginative studies of otherwise basic human behavior and a self-professed talent for interpreting data. He is perhaps most widely recognized for his proposal that emotional experience is a combination of a psychological state and a cognitive interpretation of that state.
Dr. Schachter was born in Flushing, New York to Jewish immigrant parents of eastern European origin on April 15, 1922. He was first introduced to social psychology at Yale University where he obtained his bachelor's and master's degrees. In his autobiography, published as part of A History of Psychology in Autobiography, he notes his good fortune at arriving at Yale during World War II, when most of the psychology department faculty and graduate students were involved elsewhere with wartime research. As a result, the young Schachter was admitted to graduate seminars and allowed to participate in the few research efforts that continued during the war years. These privileges cemented his interest in social psychology and paved the way for his successful career.
After completing his masters degree he left Yale to begin his doctorate in 1946 at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT). While there, he worked under the auspices of the Research Center for Group Dynamics. When the Center's founding faculty member died, MIT refused to continue funding the Center and Schachter and his fellow graduate students spent a year in search of a university to house the research center. The University of Michigan was one of those interested institutions and according to Schachter, it "apparently made the best, or perhaps the only, offer, and we all moved, kit and kaboodle (whatever they are) to Ann Arbor." He arrived at the University of Michigan in 1949 and left one year later, doctorate in hand, to accept an assistant professorship at the University of Minnesota. It was there that Dr. Schachter finished his pivotal book The Psychology of Affiliation. He submitted it to the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Social Psychological competition, and won first prize and lifelong recognition as a prominent scholar. Universities began to woo him as a result of his newfound fame. He taught at the University of Amsterdam and Stanford University before joining Columbia University's psychology faculty in 1961. He became the Robert Johnston Niven Professor of Social Psychology in 1966 and retired from Columbia in 1992.
In addition to the AAAS prize, Dr. Schachter won many awards during his career, including the James McKeen Cattell Award, and awards from the American Psychological Association and the Society for Experimental Social Psychology. He was elected to the American Academy for the Arts and Sciences in 1976. Dr. Schachter died on June 7, 1997.
The papers of Dr. Stanley Schachter are divided into four series: Publications and papers, Research Correspondence and Notes, Journals and other professional activities, and Biographical/personal.
The papers were first arranged by Dr. Schachter's wife, Sophia Schachter, before arriving at the Bentley Historical Library. Included in some folders are lists compiled by Mrs. Schachter detailing their contents. In some cases, she has also included a brief history of who worked with Dr. Schachter on certain projects.
Subjects:
Schachter, Stanley, 1922-1997; Social psychology.; Columbia University--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Schachter, Stanley, 1922-1997
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Publications and Papers 1945-1994
  Publications and Papers is comprised solely of books and papers compiled from Dr. Schachter's research which spanned a vast number of interests and years. From 1945 to 1994, Dr. Schachter published on such topics as the psychology of stock market trends, obesity, and smoking. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - "Night Vision Trainer," 1945 (Box 1)
  - "Effect of Inter-Sensory Stimulation on Dark Adaptation and Night Vision," 1949 (Box 1)
  - "Methodology of Studying Rumor Transmission," 1950 (Box 1)
  - Social Pressures in Informal Groups, 1950 (Box 1)
  - "Theory and Experiment in Social Communication," 1950 (Box 1)
  - "Deviation, Rejection, and Communication," 1951 (Box 1)
  - "Experimental Study on Cohesiveness and Productivity," 1951 (Box 1)
  - "On Group Cohesiveness," 1952 (Box 1)
  - "Cross National Research: A Case Study," 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Interpretative and Methodological Problems of Replicated Research," 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Cross Cultural Experiments on Threat and Rejection," 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Cross-Cultural Experimental Research: Methodological Problems and Factual Finding in an International Study in Group Behavior," 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Field Experiment on Rumor Transmission," 1955 (Box 1)
  - Article on Group Dynamics. American People's Encyclopedia 1956 (Box 1)
  - When Prophecy Fails, 1956 (Box 1)
  - The Psychology of Affiliation, 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Emotional Disruption and Industrial Productivity," 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Cognitive, Social, and Physiological Determinants of Emotional State," 1962 (Box 1)
  - "Epinephrine, Chlorpromazine, and Amusement," 1962 (Box 1)
  - "Adrenaline and Avoidance Learning," 1962 (Box 1)
  - "Birth Order, Eminence, and Higher Education," 1963 (Box 1)
  - "Interaction of Cognitive and Physiological Determinants of Emotional State," 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Birth Order and Sociometric Choice," 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Crime, Cognition, and the Autonomic Nervous System," 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Cognitive Manipulation of Pain," 1966 (Box 1)
  - "Cognitive Effects on Bodily Functioning: Studies of Obesity and Eating," 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Obesity and Eating," 1968 (Box 1)
  - "Effects of Fear, Food Deprivation, and Obesity on Eating," 1968 (Box 1)
  - "Manipulated Time and Eating Behavior," 1968 (Box 1)
  - "Yom Kippur, Air France, Dormitory Food, and the Eating Behavior of Obese and Normal Persons," 1968 (Box 1)
  - "Discussion of Dr. Bruch's paper," 1970 (Box 1)
  - "Assumption of Identity and Peripheralist-centralist Controversies in (Box 1)
  - "Motivation and Emotion," 1970 (Box 1)
  - "Eat, Eat," 1971 (Box 1)
  - Emotion, Obesity, and Crime, 1971 (Box 1)
  - "Some Extraordinary Facts about Obese Humans and Rats," 1971 (Box 1)
  - "Nesbitt's Paradox," 1973 (Box 1)
  - "Appetite Regulation in Obese Subjects," 1974 (Box 1)
  - Obese Humans and Rats, 1974 (Box 1)
  - "Cognition and Peripheralist-centralist Controversies in Motivation and Emotion," 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Effects of Cue Prominence and Palatability on the Drinking Behavior of Obese and Normal Humans," 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Studies of the Interaction of Psychological and Pharmacological Determinants of Smoking," 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Pharmacological and Psychological Determinants of Cigarette Smoking," 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Second Thoughts on Biological and Psychological Explanations of Behavior," 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Sin and Error in Science," 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Comments on the Maslach and Marshall-Zimbardo experiments 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Regulation, Withdrawal, and Nicotine Addiction," 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Urinary pH and the Psychology of Nicotine Addiction," 1980 (Box 1)
  - "Non-psychological Explanations of Behavior," 1980 (Box 1)
  - "Self-Treatment of Smoking and Obesity," 1981 (Box 1)
  - "Don't Sell Habit-Breakers Short: Recidivism and Self-Cure of Smoking and Obesity," 1982 (Box 1)
  - "Was the South Sea Bubble a Random Walk?," 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Random and Non-Random Walks on the New York Stock Exchange," 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Some Causes and Consequences of Dependence and Independence in the Stock Market," 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Aggregate Variables in Psychology and Economics Dependence and the Stock Market," 1987 (Box 1)
  - A Distinctive Approach to Psychological Research: The Influence of Stanley Schachter, 1987 (Box 1)
  - "Effects of Trend and of Profit or Loss on the Tendency to Sell Stock," 1987 (Box 1)
  - Extending Psychological Frontiers: Selected Works of Leon Festinger, 1989 (Box 1)
  - "Reply to Cohen et al.," 1990 (Box 1)
  - "Filled Pauses and Gestures: It's not coincidence," 1991 (Box 1)
  - "Speech, Disfluency, and the Structure of Knowledge," 1991 (Box 1)
  - "Cocaine Decreases self-control in rats," 1992 (Box 1)
  - "Vocabularies of Academia," 1994 (Box 1)
  - "Leon Festinger, A Biographical Memoir," 1994 (Box 1)
- Research Correspondence and Notes 1951-1993
  Research Correspondence and Notes contains notes Dr. Schachter kept regarding his research, surveys and questionnaires developed for research purposes, correspondence between colleagues, friends, and publishers about his work, and manuscript drafts. Also included are a handful of unpublished articles.
  - "Deviation, Rejection, and Communication," 1951 (Box 2)
  - "Experimental Study of Human Behavior," 1951 (Box 2)
  - "On Group Cohesiveness," 1952 (Box 2)
  - "Cross-Cultural Experimentation on Threat and Rejection," 1954 (Box 2)
  - "Field Experiment on Rumor Transmission," 1955 (Box 2)
  - Psychology of Affiliation
    - Correspondence with publisher 1959-1963 (Box 2)
    - Reviews 1959 (Box 2)
    - Outline undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - "Emotional Disruption and Industrial Productivity"
    - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
  - Prisoner isolation interviews 1958 (Box 2)
  - Stillwater, Minnesota prison study 1961 (Box 2)
  - "Cognitive, Social, and Physiological Determinants of Emotional State," 1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "Epinephrine, Chlorpromazine, and Amusement," 1962 (Box 2)
  - Bordentown, Minnesota prison experiment 1962 (Box 2)
  - Anxiety and affliliative motive experiment undated (Box 2)
  - Anxiety, time-perception experiment undated (Box 2)
  - "Birth Order, Eminence, and Higher Education," 1963 (Box 2)
  - "Birth Order and Sociometric Choice," 1963 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Birth Order Correspondence 1959-1969 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - "Social Pressures on Informal Groups," 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - "Crime, Cognition, and the Autonomic Nervous System," 1964 (Box 2)
  - "Interaction of Cognitive and Physiological Determinants of Emotional State," 1964 (Box 2)
  - "Cognitive Manipulation of Pain," 1966 (Box 2)
  - "Cognitive Effects on Bodily Functioning: Studies of Obesity and Eating," 1967 (Box 2)
  - "Taste Deprivation and Weight Determination," 1967 (Box 2)
  - "Yom Kippur, Air France, and Dormitory Food," 1967 (Box 2)
  - "Effects of Fear, Food Deprivation, and Obesity on Eating," 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Manipulated Time and Eating Behavior," 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Obesity and Eating," 1968 (Box 3)
  - "Cognition and Peripheralist-Centralist Controversies in Motivation and Emotion," 1969 (Box 3)
  - "Emotion, Obesity, and Crime," 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - "Eat, Eat," 1971 (Box 3)
  - "Some Extraordinary Facts about Obese Humans," 1971 (Box 3)
  - "Appetite Regulation in Obese Subjects," 1972 (Box 3)
  - "Nesbitt's Paradox," 1973 (Box 3)
  - Obese Humans and Rats, 1974, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - "Studies in the Interaction of Psychological and Pharmacological Determinants of Smoking," 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "Some Replies to Schnur," 1977 (Box 3)
  - "Urinary pH and the Psychology of Nicotine Addiction," 1977 (Box 3)
  - "Pharmacological and Psychological Determinants of Smoking," 1978 (Box 3)
  - "Regulation, Withdrawal, and Nicotine Addiction," 1978 (Box 3)
  - "Second Thoughts on Biological and Psychological Explanations of Behavior," 1978 (Box 3)
  - Maslach, Marshall-Zimbardo experiment, comments 1979 (Box 3)
  - "Self-Treatment of Smoking and Obesity," 1980 (Box 3)
  - "Don't Sell Habit-Breakers Short: Recidivism and the Self-Cure of Smoking and Obesity," 1982 (Box 3)
  - Stock market articles 1982 (Box 3)
  - Zeitgeist data notes 1983 (Box 3)
  - "Stock market correspondence 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - "Aggregate Variables in Psychology and Economics," 1984 (Box 3)
  - "Studies of Dependent and Interdependent Markets," 1985 (Box 3)
  - "Effects of Trend and of Profit or Loss on the Tendency to Sell Stock," 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Filled Pauses and Gestures, notes 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Extending Psychological Frontiers: Selected Works of Leon Festinger, preface, 1988 (Box 4)
  - "A Reply to Cohen, Lichtenstein et al.," 1989 (Box 4)
  - Leon Festinger, biographical memoir 1990 (Box 4)
  - "Speech Disfluency and the Structure of Knowledge," 1990 (Box 4)
  - "Vocabularies of Academia," 1993 (Box 4)
- Journals and other Professional Activities
  Journals and other Professional Activities contains correspondence with publishers, article reviews, the activities of various committees Dr. Schachter was involved with, transcripts from taped meetings. and several lectures he delivered to colleagues.
  - Teaching methods of Sociometry 1951, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Cross-National Program of the Organization for Comparative Social Research
    - 1952-1953, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Review of articles for Sociometry, 1955-1960 (Box 4)
  - "Group Dynamics," encyclopedia summary 1957 (Box 4)
  - New York City prison study, proposed 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, correspondence, 1963-1971 (Box 4)
  - "Social Cohesion," encyclopedia entry 1964 (Box 4)
  - Social psychology series, correspondence
    - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968-1972 (Box 4)
  - Social Science Research Council Committee (SSRCC) on Biological Bases of Social Behavior
    - 1967-1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1974-1979 (Box 5)
    - Final Report 1979 (Box 5)
  - Philip Morris Company, correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 5)
  - Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers, correspondence 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - Proposed conference on smoking, correspondence 1973 (Box 5)
  - "Methodology: The Psychologist and the Experiment, movie script 1974 (Box 5)
  - Guggenheim fellowship application (withdrawn) 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - "Nicotine as Addicting Agent: Comments on Dr. Russell's paper," 1977 (Box 5)
  - "Springtime, Suicide, and Wills," unpublished paper 1978 (Box 5)
  - Transcript from MIT Research Center for Group Dynamics reunion 1978 (Box 5)
  - This Week's Citation Classic 1979 (Box 5)
  - Banality and the Stock Market, lecture 1981 (Box 5)
  - Sloan grant proposals 1981, 1986, 1989 (Box 5)
  - More on recidivism 1982 (Box 5)
  - State of Psychology, conference report 1982 (Box 5)
  - "Curbing Coronaries by Press Conference, unpublished paper 1984 (Box 5)
  - Cognition and Emotion Panel, report 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Unpublished articles with Rose and Zetterberg undated (Box 5)
- Biographical/Personal
  Awards and honors, several interviews, correspondence about his appointment at Columbia University, fond letters from former students, obituaries, and two informal portraits make up the Biographical/Personal series.
  - Awards and honors (Box 5)
  - Columbia University appointment, correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous biographical (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence
    - 1944-1954 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1990 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - New Scientist, interview, 1975 (Box 5)
  - The Making of Social Psychology, interview, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Obituaries 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Photographs- Informal portraits of Schachter (Box 5)
  - Student correspondence 1968-1996 (scattered) (Box 5)
Related Material
The papers of Leon Festinger, a prominent social psychologist at the University of Michigan, and a contemporary of Schachter's, are also preserved at the Bentley Historical Library. These two collections provide an comparative overview of the field of social psychology from 1950 to 1980.